Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is מ"ח, mem-chet, we
pick up in the middle of מ"ז עמוד ב' mem-zayin amud-bet by
the two dots about ten lines down, and we are now in
the core part of the מסכת masechet that deals with the כתובה
kesuvah per se and the reciprocal
obligation and
or I should say the rights and responsibilities that the husband has
to his wife and then we'll get to the issue about the
wife to the husband.
And the משנה mishna first focused on the father's rights over his
daughter and power and rights to annul the vows, to marry her
off, the rights to her earnings, most of which are biblical.
And the father actually has no responsibilities, we mentioned yesterday he doesn't
even have responsibility to feed his
daughter, presumably can't let her starve, but he could send her out
of the house and go ahead and tell her to earn her
own keep. And then we transfer from the girl transfers from the
father's house to the groom's house after אירוסין, erusin, after betrothal she's
still fundamentally in the father's house and it's the moment of נישואין
nissuin when she begins to live together with her husband, which is
where the really the primary obligations of the and rights and responsibilities
of the כתובה kesuvah kick in and now she's basically out of
her father's house into the groom's house and we're going to deal
with that coming up in the next משנה mishna as the focus
on basically what constitutes נישואין. nissuin. And as we mentioned yesterday, sorry,
he's just doing this, as we mentioned yesterday, sorry, the
this מסכת masechet really deals with the idea of the daughter
and so on of the woman in the sense one gets reading
the תורה, Torah, which is that she never is independent. She goes
out of one man's house to another man's house, out of her
father's house to her husband's house. The תורה Torah never has a
woman basically living independently even after, for example, the woman's husband dies,
by the daughter of a כהן kohen it says ושבה אל בית
אביה כנעוריה, v'shava el beit aviha kine'ureha, right? Somebody's asked me about
that the other day, she returns to her father's house. But certainly
would never have her, sort of, directing her own fate like as
an autonomous agent.
And it's always the father that marries her off, it's the rabbis
that come and say that that stops when she's a נערה, na'arah,
when she's a בוגרת, bogeret, that stops when she passes puberty and
it's 12 and a half and then she actually can become emancipated
from her father and become her
own independent and her own legal agent. And so and that's why
מסכת קידושין masechet kiddushin mostly is the woman marrying herself off, but
again, it should be noticed that it's rabbis that open up that
whole
space and it's not in the תורה Torah and our and right
here we're dealing without that space, basically going from the husband's house
to the from the father's house to the husband's house. So now
within the issue about the husband's house, we had a discussion at
the end of yesterday about whether the כתובה kesuvah rights and responsibilities,
how much do they kick in between אירוסין erusin and נישואין. nissuin.
There's the base responsibility of the 100 or 200 amount of the
כתובה kesuvah that exists from the time of אירוסין erusin but whether
the other amounts, whether it's the dowry or whether it's the תוספת
tosefes kicks in before the נישואין nissuin was debated. And now we
turn to the key issue of what those ongoing rights and responsibilities
are. And we should mention that there are two sort of names
for this: the basic 100, 200 and the תוספת, tosefes, that's like
called, thank you, the עיקר כתובה ikkar kesuvah and the תוספת, tosefes,
the lump sum payment, the major amount that's paid again at the
time of divorce or death of the husband, which serves essentially as
an alimony or in the case of death of the husband as
a substitute for an inheritance because the wife does not inherit her
husband as a way of protecting her if she is left without
a man, without the protection of her husband. That's the עיקר ikkar
and the תוספת, tosefes, the base amount plus whatever additional amount the
groom obligates himself in. But the ongoing responsibilities and rights during marriage
are called the תנאי כתובה. t'nai kesuvah. תנאי t'nai not in the
sense of like a condition, but in sense of like
I don't know what, stipulation, stipulations, right. So the ongoing obligations of
the כתובה kesuvah during marriage. And the one we mentioned already yesterday
was that he gets the אוכל פירות. ochel peiros. The property that
is not the dowry, but property that is the dowry is the
נכסי צאן ברזל, nichsei tzon barzel, she brings the she transfers the
title to her husband, but rather property that she owns at the
time of marriage that she retains the title to, the נכסי מלוג,
nichsei milug, there he has the right of getting the benefit from
that, the פירות, peiros, the the earnings off of that property. But
now we're going to get to more of the to the whole
range of those things. So let's take a look middle of מ"ז
עמוד ב'. mem-zayin amud-bet. חייב במזונותיה, chayav b'mezonoteha, he's obligated to feed
her, though that's his obligation.
So תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, thank you, oh, good coffee. תקנו מזונותיה
תחת מעשה ידיה. Tiknu mezonoteha tachat maaseh yadeha. They established his obligation
to feed her in exchange for her earnings. וקבורתה תחת כתובתה, Ukvorata
tachat ktuvata, and his obligation to bury
her in exchange for the fact that the כתובה, ktubah, which here
means the, again, it's a funny word כתובתה, ktuvata, but it means
the dowry, the נדוניא, nedunya, the basic property listed in the כתובה.
ktubah.
לפיכך בעל אוכל פירות. Lefikach baal ochel perot. So therefore, the husband
eats the fruit. So the גמרא Gemara asks: פירות מאן דכר שמיה?
Perot man dchar shemei? Who's talking about the fruit? It's either talking
about the dowry which she brings the entire property into the estate
and transfers title, or it's talking about her earnings. Who's talking about
fruit, which is earnings are like, you know, wages. Fruit is means
what she, what the interest or, you know, the earnings off of
the holdings. So the גמרא Gemara says: חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. Chasurei
mechasra vehachi katani. It's missing some words in here so it should
be taught: תקנו מזונותיה תחת מעשה ידיה. Tiknu mezonoteha tachat maaseh yadeha.
So he has to feed her in exchange for her earnings. The
earnings here is like through her labor. ופרקונה תחת פירות, Upirkona tachat
perot,
which is what we discussed yesterday, he has to redeem her in
exchange for the fact that he earns money that he keeps the
earnings off of her holdings. וקבורתה תחת כתובתה, Ukvorata tachat ktuvata, and
he has to bury her, she predeceases him,
in exchange for the dowry. And we're going to discuss why exactly
it's these types of parallels. Now, לפיכך בעל אוכל פירות, lefikach baal
ochel perot, and therefore the husband eats the fruit. So why does
it mention again, even if you stick in the idea of the
fruit in exchange for the redeeming her, why is it mention the
'therefore'? Why is that more of a
'therefore' than any of the other than any of the three? So
the גמרא Gemara says: מאי לפיכך? Mai lefikach? מהו דתימא אימר פירא
לא נכלינהו ואנוחי ננחינהו. Mah d'teima eimar pira lo nichlinhu v'anochei nanchinhu.
Since the fruit is, the reason he gets to keep the earnings
off of her property is in order to make sure that he
will redeem her if she's taken captive, maybe to make it more
sure that he'll redeem her is we should say take all those
earnings and put them in escrow, right? Don't go ahead and use
them. Any money that she earns, any interest off of her, you
know, off of her stock portfolio or whatever, go ahead and put
that in a separate account, an emergency account, so if she's taken
captive then you'll use that money. Why can he go ahead and
spend it and buy himself a Ferrari or whatever he's going to
do? So let's say ננחינהו. nanchinhu. No, we're not going to do
that.
ואי אם כן מימנע ולא פריק V'ee im ken mimna v'lo parik
because if you don't put in a separate account then he won't
redeem her because he's already used up that money. קא משמע לן.
Ka mashma lan. No, that's why we want him to eat the
פירות. perot. Why? דהדיפא. De'hadifa. It's better that he use that money.
זימנין דלא מלו. Zimnin d'lo malu. Sometimes if we would have it
in a separate emergency account, so let's say this emergency account would
have $10,000 in it off of all the money that she's been
earning from her stock portfolio, and then the captives are asking for
$20,000, so
he'll say 'I'll pay 10,000'. So they'll say 'No, sorry, no deal'.
He'll say 'Fine, whatever, keep her'. So therefore, if you have it
as separate money, he'll figure that's the end of my obligation.
And therefore he won't redeem her if it's more.
ופריק לה מדידיה. Ufarik lah midedei.
And he'll therefore, he'll stick his hand into his own pocket. If
the money was separate, then he'll say I'll only give the money
that's been saved up for her. But if he's been using the
money all along for the last 10 years, so we're not exactly
keeping a strict accounting, and he understands that that money he has
a right to use, it might be that he never has to
spend it on her and he'll be able to keep it all
for himself, or it might be that sometimes the cost to redeem
her will be more than he took out of it. But he
understands that's the nature of it. It's not just money held and
it's segregated for her, and then it would be limited to that
money. He has unlimited rights to it however much it is, but
we're not keeping a strict accounting, and therefore when it's time to
redeem her, we don't also keep a strict accounting and he has
to go ahead and redeem her whatever it costs. So again, for
us it's hard to relate to this, that it seems like such
a regular ongoing benefit, and this idea that he'll have to redeem
her, a, that that would come up on a not rare basis
seems clear because we keep on talking about it in this מסכת,
masechet, but it's hard for us to relate to. And b, the
idea that he would hesitate before redeeming his wife, you know, maybe
it has to do with how good their relationship is and whether
he values his money more, but also as I pointed out yesterday,
the fact that she might be raped and the cost, or maybe
even will actively, will willingly have sex in this case in order
to try to get her freedom, is something that might make him
hesitate. It's an interesting reflection on the nature of marriage and the
nature of society, these realities. But one minute, so those are the
three things though that we... But one minute, so those are the
three things though that we've mentioned, and we're going to discuss in
a minute why exactly they match up like that, we've already discussed
a little bit yesterday. But the first one I want to make
before we get to the concrete things and how they match up
is what is in exchange for what? Meaning the idea, does it
start with his rights and in exchange for his rights he has
responsibilities, or does it start in the reverse? Our framing of it
makes it start
like תקנו מזונותיה תחת מעשה ידיה Tiknu Mezonoteha Tachat Maaseh Yadeha that
it starts with he's entitled to her earnings and therefore in exchange
they said he has to feed her. Okay, now why is that
important? Because you could say the reverse. It starts with his responsibility
to feed her and in exchange they gave him her earnings. The
reason it matters is because who is basically the party that is
being protected? Who could opt out? Exactly. If basically he has rights
to her earnings then and but okay once I'm taking her earnings
I'm going to feed her, then he is the entitled party and
therefore he is the one that could say he wants to opt
out. You know what? Keep your earnings and I won't feed you
because it's ultimately his right. However, if you say it the reverse
way, it's her right. She has a right to be supported and
fed and provided for and in exchange he keeps her earnings. So
then she's the one entitled to say, you know what? Don't feed
me and I'll keep my own earnings. And that's very important because
you know especially nowadays, I mean for us this is all hypothetical,
but in Israel actually the כתובה Ketubah is a binding legal document
where they actually will wind up using, you know, depending if you
go to a בית דין Beit Din or a בית משפט Beit
Mishpat and so on. So therefore can the woman say, because you
know now at the time of the תורה Torah and at the
time of חזל Chazal it was a very progressive document because basically
you had the idea that he had actual responsibilities towards his wife,
her interests were being protected. Okay, but nowadays, you know, it's nice
that it's reciprocal, but there's a difference between being reciprocal and being
parallel, right? It's not the same. It's like, you know, my earnings
and you provide... how about we pool our earnings and we're mutually
responsible to one another's, you know, upkeep and well-being and hospital bills
and so on. So actually, and let's say the woman is a
higher earner than the husband, right? So she'd rather keep her own
earnings. Forget it, I don't want you to support me, I'm going
to keep my own earnings and I'll support myself. So actually what
we wind up concluding against the way this גמרא Gemara sounds, where
it sounds like he's basically the empowered, the entitled party, is we
basically view that she's the entitled party. She's the one that's entitled
to being supported and in exchange he gets her earnings and therefore
she's entitled to say I'm going to keep my own earnings and
you keep your food bills, you keep your support. And therefore for
example קולך, Kolech, which is a women's orthodox women's organization in Israel,
has created a new כתובה Ketubah or it's like a rider to
the כתובה Ketubah which basically says that first the wife says I'm
going to keep my earnings and I'm going to keep all this
stuff on my own and I'm going to keep all the earnings
off of my, you know, my wages and my holdings and all
of that and you don't have any responsibilities to me. And that
she's entitled if we say that fundamentally she's the party that's being
protected. And then they could both say to one another, now everybody's
keeping all their own earnings and nobody owes anything to anybody else.
And then they make a second or a third, if you would,
sort of obligation and it says, and now we're going to obligate
ourselves to pool all of our earnings and to be mutually responsible
to one another for all of the, you know, these types of
obligations. Okay, but that's all in her hands to decide whether or
not to do if we say that she's fundamentally the protected party
as opposed to the way this ברייתא Braita made it sound like,
which is a little of the reverse. Now there were some questions.
We'll start with Dov, yeah. My first question is just when the
marriage dissolves through divorce or through death, so does the נכסי
צאן ברזל Nikhsei Tzon Barzel go back to her?
Well, not necessarily the actual property itself, but their value at the
time of the wedding. Yes, which is why the amount is written
into the כתובה. Ketubah. Okay. And the second... if he dies. If
she dies, then he inherits her. Right. This word למלאות, Lemalot, what's
למלא... Lemalo... what's the word למלאות? Lemalot? To fill up. למלאות. Lemalot.
Ah,
it doesn't fill the amount. I see. Thank you. My question was,
so maybe sociologically it seems like, you know, it was very common
for her to, you know, get a job or something like that,
because otherwise why would they say תקנו מזונותיה תחת מעשה ידיה? Tiknu
Mezonoteha Tachat Maaseh Yadeha? One or two times that she actually gets
a job. Right, right, meaning, so the question is how much? I
mean, I don't think it would be like a nine-to-five job outside
of the house. She might be like a seamstress or she might
be, you know, those types of things or might be even work
that she does in the house.
מעשה ידיה Maaseh Yadeha would also include... exactly, would also include domestic
work, yes. Kolech organization, is that... those stipulations you just mentioned, do
they put that into the... No, so that's the thing. The כתובה
Ketubah now has become more of a ritual document, you know, although
again, the irony is that in Israel on the one hand, it's
ritual... So that nobody wants to change the language in any substantive
way and on the other hand in Israel they wind up using
it as a legal document as well. So they make it as
a set they make the stipulations in a separate document outside of
the actual כתובה Ketubah itself. Okay so now let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. So now we have to figure out exactly
why this linking up is about the A for B, why is
it A for A prime B for B prime, what's exactly the
matching? So the
גמרא Gemara says okay ואפכנא Ve'apchana let me reverse it, I mean
not literally reverse but let me say that I don't know the
מזונות Mezonos is
for the whatever is for the פירות Peiros or something. So אמר
אביי Amar Abaye תקנו מצוי למצוי ושאינו מצוי לשאינו מצוי. Tiknu matzui
l'matzui ve'she'eino matzui l'she'eino matzui. Okay we established the common for the
common and the not common for the not common. So what are
the things that we have basically and then I also want to
show you in terms of the language of the כתובה. Ketuvah. We
have the most common is מזונות, Mezonos, that's your daily food bills.
So that's כנגד מעשי ידיה keneged Ma'asei yadehah which is her earnings,
whether she's earning money out of the house which probably was less
common, but it's even labor that she does in the house.
She's a homemaker or she's making all the clothes for the family
and she's doing all the cooking or whatever she's doing. Okay so
that's common for common. Then
you have קבורה, Kevurah, he'll pay
for the funeral bill תחת כתובתה tachas Ketuvatah which is basically means
נדוניא Nidunyah which is dowry. That I find is quite interesting
because the dowry I mean I guess you say common, I mean
50% of the times she'll die before him. Okay but still כתובתה
Ketuvatah you imagine the dowry is like a significant amount and that's
a 100% of the time but I don't know if it's 100%,
I mean it might be small in a poor family. The other
interesting thing though is that this is ongoing and this is a
one-time thing.
There's a one-time cost for the funeral, there's a one-time amount of
property that's being brought in. And then you have
פירקונה Pirkonah which is redeeming her if she's taken captive תחת פירות.
tachas Peiros. So that's also interesting because this is a one-time thing,
this is ongoing, but again as the גמרא Gemara said this might
be a very high amount and this maybe is a slow accrual
of things. So we want that to be like we're not keeping
an exact accounting. You might wind up taking the פירות Peiros and
never have to pay for redeeming her or you might have to
go ahead and redeem her and you won't have the earnings opposite
the פירות. Peiros. Okay but again it is interesting that this is
considered רש״י Rashi says it's somewhat uncommon because almost like every woman
brings in a נדוניא Nidunyah in terms of a fixed amount but
פירות Peiros would be stuff probably less things that the father would
give her as a נדוניא Nidunyah to bring into the marriage and
more property
or a portfolio that she already had a title to she already
owned at the time of marriage. So nowadays for example especially a
woman's professional woman or whatever she probably much more has property that
she has a title to rather than money that's being given as
a נדוניא. Nidunyah. Okay but in the time of the גמרא Gemara
the נדוניא Nidunyah was very common whereas property that סתם stam she
just had a title to that she happened to own while she
was getting married that she retained title to and he earned the
פירות Peiros that was less common. Okay so those are the matching
ups. Now I want to say something also about where we get
this in terms of the language of the כתובה Ketuvah just briefly,
I mean it's interesting maybe we'll hand out a whole כתובה Ketuvah
but just briefly to understand what the כתובה Ketuvah is, כתובה Ketuvah
is
like באחד בשבת B'echad Be'shabbat שנת shenat blah blah blah blah. Some
כתובות Ketuvot say by the way אנן סהדי Anan Sahadi which is
actually we testify that or
באחד בשבת אנן סהדי די B'echad Be'shabbat Anan Sahadi de it's basically
because it's the witnesses testifying. Right so it says but we don't
have that the אשכנזים Ashkenazim don't. Anyway so-and-so אמר לה להדא בתולתא,
Amar lah l'hada Betulta, אמר לה להדא בתולתא, Amar lah l'hada Betulta,
הוי לי לאינתו. havi li l'intu. So on this day they got
married so that's basically saying they got married. Okay now by the
way actually it's קידושין, kiddushin, הוי לי לאינתו havi li l'intu because
the כתובה Ketubah obligations come after קידושין kiddushin like at the time
of
נישואין, nissuin, הוי לי לאינתו havi li l'intu which הוי לי לאינתו
havi li l'intu be for me as a wife.
They got married. Okay okay הוי לי לאינתו havi li l'intu ואנא
va'ana and now here comes the stipulation ואנא va'ana אפלח ואוקיר eflach
v'okir
ואיזון ve'ezon
ואפרנס ve'afarnes
ליכי
ליכי lichi lichi כהלכת גוברין
יהודאין. ke'hilchat guvrin yehuda'in. Thank you. Done in front of in front
of in front of some thing בקושטא. b'kushta. Okay ויהיבנא ליכי, ve'yehavna
lichi, ויהיבנא ליכי, ve'yehavna lichi, ויהיבנא ליכי ve'yehavna lichi מהר בתולייכי mohar
betulaichi כסף זוזי. kesef zuzei. דחזי ליכי מדאורייתא d'chazi lichi m'deoraisa blah
blah blah blah
blah
ומעייל
לותייכי כארח
כל ארעא, u'me'ayel lavasayichi k'orach kol ar'a,
כארח כל ארעא. k'orach kol ar'a.
So the רב rav never actually goes through the text of the
כתובה? ketubah? No. Okay. So basically what you have here is, okay,
this is the מוהר. mohar. Notice by the way מוהר, mohar, which
is the עיקר כתובה, ikar ketubah, which is the 200 זוז. zuz.
Okay? And that's דחזי ליכי. d'chazi lichi. There's a question about מדאורייתא,
m'deoraisa, right, whether כתובה ketubah is מדאורייתא m'deoraisa or not, and how
much is it based on the biblical מוהר. mohar. Okay. This is
ומעייל לותייכי כארח כל ארעא u'me'ayel lavasayichi k'orach kol ar'a is sex,
like ביאה, bi'ah, to enter. Okay. I will, I will literally, I
will enter onto you, into thee or onto thee in the natural
way, okay, as is the way of all of all of flesh
if you will. Okay. So this is, this is sex, which is
the מצוה mitzvah of עונה. onah. Okay. And here, which we'll get
to in a minute. Okay. So here, אפלח eflach ואוקיר ve'okir we're
not really going to discuss. Right? This is כבוד. kavod. חייב אדם
לכבד את אשתו
יותר מגופו. chayav adam l'chaved es ishto yoser m'gufo. You know, לאהוב
אשתו כגופו ולכבדה יותר מגופו, le'ehov ishto k'gufo u'l'chabda yoser m'gufo, etc.
So this is not a financial obligation, but to show respect to
your wife. Okay. Work for your wife is interesting. Right? אפלח eflach
means what? Work. Oh. אפלח eflach means to bow, doesn't it? Yeah,
yeah, but to worship, yeah, it can, but that's not what it
means here. Okay. I will go out and work, you know?
What? Oh yeah, there you go. עבודה. avodah. Right. Okay. So meaning,
I will go out and I'll earn a living, okay, for you.
Okay, but this is more personal. But this is the sort of
things we're talking about, מזונות mezonos and פרנסה. parnasah. Okay? So what's
the difference between מזונות mezonos and פרנסה? parnasah? פרנסה parnasah might be
clothing. Okay? So that's מזונות mezonos and פרנסה, parnasah, which probably means
כסות. ksus. Okay? So here you have, right, מזונות, mezonos, כסות, ksus,
עונה. onah. You have these obligations. Okay? So what's not mentioned? You've
got מזונות. mezonos. What you don't have mentioned is רפואה refuah and
קבורה. kvurah. Those actually are not explicitly mentioned. Okay? What's also not
mentioned is his right to these things. Okay? It's gonna... it does
mention the כתובה. ketubah. ודין נדוניא דהנעלת ליה מבי אבוה. v'den nedunya
d'hanalas leh mibei avuha. Right? ודין נדוניא דהנעלת ליה מבי אבוה. v'den
nedunya d'hanalas leh mibei avuha. Right? This is
the נדוניא. nedunya. This is the dowry that she brought from the
father's house. Then you list it. So normally you would say: two
goats, you know,
ten dresses, one camel, whatever. But we don't list it. Right? But
we don't list it. We say בין בכסף בין בדהב, bein b'chesef
bein b'dehav, whatever it is. We're not going to list it nowadays.
They used to list it. הכל קיבל עליו חתן דנא במאה זקוקין
כסף צרוף. hakol kibel alav chasan dena b'me'ah zkukan kesef tzaruf. So
basically what he's saying is, and I'll speak a little bit about
how, how come we fix it? We're going to say the dowry
is a fixed amount. We're going to fix the amount. Meaning it
used to be that it would be what it really would be.
But we're just going to say, here's how much it is. It's
going to be a fixed amount of 100 כסף צרוף. kesef tzaruf.
That's much more than a זוז. zuz. Okay? כסף צרוף. kesef tzaruf.
Okay, so rather... so this, we're going to fix the amount of
the dowry to be this fixed amount. That is the עיקר כתובה.
ikar ketubah. That is
that. Okay? And that's the fixed amount. It does not mention... it
would never mention the... that she would retain title to, he would
get the פירות, peiros, but you wouldn't have to list... it had...
it's just in her name. But this is the stuff that she
actually brought in and transferred title, and if she ever go... if
he dies or he divorces her, she gets to take the value
of this back out of the estate. So what's the value? So
you have to write in the כתובה ketubah how much that value
is. And therefore you fix what she brought in. So we're going
to... normally you would say, okay, like I said: two sheep, three
goats, etc., it's worth X amount. But we just say, we're not
going to figure out exactly what she brought in. We're going to
fix the amount at 100 כסף צרוף. kesef tzaruf. But now, I
guess since I'm already talking about it, I'll tell you why we
fix the amount. Because in the time of the ראשונים, rishonim,
the כתובה ketubah was a real legal document, and 200 זוז zuz
had become almost worthless. And the woman's interests weren't protected. So what
they did in order to protect the woman's interest was they effectively
replaced 200 זוז zuz with 100 כסף צרוף. kesef tzaruf. כסף צרוף
kesef tzaruf is real like silver, זוז zuz was like copper... no,
well, I'll tell you how you get to 200. So there's this
parallel of 200 זוז, zuz, 100 כסף צרוף, kesef tzaruf, which was
a substantial amount which really did protect her. Now how did you
introduce that new amount into the כתובה? ketubah? So one way you
did is you said we're going to assume that the נדוניא nedunya
is already 100 כסף צרוף. kesef tzaruf. Okay, so you could have
somebody who doesn't have a penny to her name and you're saying
the נדוניא nedunya is, I don't know, $20,000, whatever 100 כסף צרוף
kesef tzaruf was. We're just going to say that's how much it
was that you brought in. Then there's another thing, because when you
deal with
the כתובה, ketubah, right, it says
כסף זוזי מאתן דחזי ליכי מדאורייתא ומזונייכי וכסותייכי וסיפוקייכי כארח כל ארעא
kesef zuzei masan d'chazi lichi m'deoraisa u'mezonayichi u'chsusayichi v'sipukayichi k'orach kol ar'a
and והוסיף לה מן דיליה v'hosif lah min deileih
עוד מאה זקוקין כסף צרוף. od me'ah zkukan kesef tzaruf. Right? Now
what's this? זקוקים צרוף. z'kukim tzaruf. This is תוספת כתובה. tosefes k'suva.
זקוקים כסף צרוף. z'kukim kesef tzaruf. This has nothing to do with
the dowry. This is the dowry. And then after we mention that
the dowry is a hundred כסף צרוף, kesef tzaruf, we say oh,
by the way, the כתובה ksuva amount we mentioned a little while
ago, the hundred or the two hundred זוז, zuz, you know, there's
this idea of תוספת כתובה tosefes k'suva that he could promise extra
in addition to the base amount? Oh, he's adding another hundred כסף
צרוף kesef tzaruf for תוספת. tosefes. So you have... well, right, and
in the Ashkenazi כתובות, k'suvos, I don't know what they did for
Sefardi, but in the Ashkenazi כתובות, k'suvos, they made this the standard
boilerplate that he has to do a תוספת tosefes of a hundred
כסף צרוף. kesef tzaruf. As a, this is a dowry and this
is a תוספת. tosefes. And therefore it says סך הכל. sach hakol.
It's very bizarre. Why are you combining the amount of the dowry
with the amount of the תוספת? tosefes? But the reason you're combining
it is because we now have two hundred כסף צרוף kesef tzaruf
to effectively replace the two hundred זוז. zuz. And this is the
way her interests were protected by doing it in this amount, which
is like silver coins, which was much more, you know, valuable than
the זוז. zuz. And therefore then we say סך הכל מאתיים זקוקים
כסף צרוף. sach hakol mas'ayim z'kukim kesef tzaruf. Okay, but really what
you have is is that that is a way we introduced it
through affixing the dowry amount and adding a fixed תוספת tosefes to
the base כתובה. ksuva. But still based on six hundred years ago.
Has there been a fix since then? No. Okay, so though the
קולח כתובה kolech ksuva is the newest fix. Okay, but the but
the basic stuff we're talking about, the ongoing obligations are here. And
interestingly, it really only, I mean, this this is mentioned, right, because
you have to give an amount. This isn't mentioned because why would
you mention it in the כתובה? ksuva? You don't have to fix
an amount. That's just an ongoing obligation. But in terms of his
responsibilities to her, interestingly, it only mentions the מזונות. m'zonos. She could
say, you could say then from this formula that part of the
כתובה ksuva is דאורייתא d'oraysa with an additional דרבנן? d'rabanan? Yeah. Right.
Exactly. Well, there's the עיקר כתובה, ikar k'suva, which is the question
if that's דאורייתא d'oraysa or דרבנן. d'rabanan. And these issues about מזונות,
m'zonos, פירות, p'ros, and עונה, onah, is that דאורייתא d'oraysa or not?
We're about to get to. Yes. It just seems like a really
interesting placement. I'm going to work, honor you, and then and feed
you. I would have thought that I, you know... Well,
you gotta work in order to pay for the food. Right. Why's
what's work doing really in the middle? It just seems kind of
weird. Yeah, well, I mean you're talking about like personal obligations as
opposed to financial obligations. But also why do we then skip the
sex till down here?
I don't know, I can't figure that out. I heard at a
Farsi wedding they sat down when they were signing before the חופה
chuppah they itemized and added the amount of the תוספת. tosefes. Yeah.
Right. Well, I was at some wedding also where they put in
an amount but it was like a crazy amount, they put in
like a million dollars, and then it was probably אסמכתא asmachta like
because it's not like somebody really could have like obligated themselves that
amount. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says like this. Okay, נחזי,
nechezi, we're going to get to, we haven't listed like which of
this is biblical, which is rabbinic, we've just listed sort of the
the you know the parallel obligations and rights. So now we're going
to get to the question about which of these obligations are biblical
or not. אמר רבא: amar Rava: האי
תנא סבר, hai tanna savar, the following תנא tanna we're about to
quote holds, מזונות מדאורייתא, m'zonos mi'd'oraysa, that מזונות m'zonos are biblical obligation.
Because before we said they obligated him מזונות m'zonos in exchange for
her earnings, right? Nobody by the way says he's earning, that she
gets he gets his earnings, her earnings biblically. The husband, the father
gets her earnings. The husband is entitled to the earnings only rabbinically.
But that made it sound like it was all rabbinic. He gets
his earnings and then they they demanded that he give her מזונות.
m'zonos. So רבא Rava is saying okay, that ברייתא braisa sounded like
מזונות m'zonos was rabbinic. The following ברייתא braisa sounds like מזונות m'zonos
is biblical. Where do you get it?
דתניא, d'tanya, we learn a ברייתא: braisa: שארה כסותה ועונתה לא יגרע,
she'erah k'susah v'onasah lo yigrah,
which by the way, we should just appreciate פשט pshat of the
פסוקים. p'sukim. פשט pshat of the פסוקים p'sukim is is that this
man take takes this underage girl or whatever this girl that her
father sold off, and the idea was for him to marry her.
If he doesn't marry her or the son doesn't marry her, she
goes free. If he does marry her, the תורה Torah says אם
אחרת יקח לו. im acheres yikach lo. So now he married this
woman through her being a slave. Then he went and he married
a woman of higher status, you know, social status, right,
and not through being a slave. So the concern was was that
the first wife that he had that he got through being a
slave, he's going to treat her in a, you know, as, you
know, in a very second class status. So the תורה Torah says,
no, even though he took a second wife, שארה כסותה ועונתה לא
יגרע. she'erah k'susah v'onasah lo yigrah. The שארה כסות ועונה, she'erah k'susah
v'onah, which we'll discuss in a minute what that means, of the
first wife, he cannot he cannot sort of decrease. He has to
give her her full due. So from there we learn the due
that's due to every wife, but it's in the context of not
decreasing it from a woman from a first wife that he would
likely give less respect and less status to than his second wife.
Okay, so what is this obligation? שארה אלו מזונות. she'erah elu m'zonos.
That means paying for the food. וכן הוא אומר, Ve-chen hu omer,
ואשר אכלו שאר עמי, Va'asher achalu she'er ami,
that they ate the flesh of my people. So the
flesh you need the food to keep the flesh on the bones.
Okay, so שארה She'erah is the food. כסותה, Kesutah, the garments, כמשמען,
K'mashma'an, that means providing for the clothes. עונתה, Onatah, her times, זה
עונה האמורה בתורה. Zeh onah ha'amurah ba-Torah.
This is the, the regular times of having sex between husband and
wife. וכן הוא אומר, Ve-chen hu omer, אם תענה בנותי, Im ta'aneh
benotai, which is a funny way place to learn it out from,
which means if you afflict my daughters by withholding sex, presumably. I
understand it means there also, I understand. I understand. Anyway, I understand.
Anyway, somehow we're making that association. Okay, so that's the classic one
that we all assume because we all read רש"י Rashi on the
חומש, Chumash, and רש"י Rashi tells us שארה כסותה ועונתה She'erah kesutah
ve-onatah means מזונות, mezonot, כסות kesut and sex. Okay, that's explanation number
one, but that's not the only one, and it might not even
be the halachic one. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, שארה זו
עונה. She'erah zo onah. No, even שארה She'erah means sex. וכן הוא
אומר, Ve-chen hu omer, איש איש אל כל שאר בשרו, Ish ish
el kol she'er besaro, every person to his closeness of flesh, לא
תקרבו לגלות ערוה, Lo tikrevu l'galot ervah,
so do not draw close to have to expose the nakedness. So
שאר she'er yes, שאר she'er is flesh, but flesh doesn't necessarily mean
making sure there's flesh on the bone and providing for the food,
flesh might mean the fleshly
relation, which is sex, right. In the context of the Torah as
opposed to going somewhere in נ"ך. Nach. Right, because the Torah means
flesh, otherwise what does שאר she'er mean? What? So רמב"ן Ramban discusses
it. רמב"ן Ramban says it could just mean a double language, but
רמב"ן Ramban also says it might mean like the closeness of flesh,
that בשר basar just means flesh, שאר she'er means like a flesh
that is close to you,
קירוב בשר Kiruv basar or something.
כסותה כמשמעו, Kesutah k'mashma'o, כסות ksut that does mean clothes. עונתה אלו
מזונות. Onatah elu mezonot. So now we're still saying the same trio:
clothes, food, and sex, but we're reversing which word learns it out
from. עונה Onah means food. How does עונה onah mean food? וכן
הוא אומר, Ve-chen hu omer, ויענך וירעיבך, Vay'anecha vayarchivcha, God caused you
to suffer and make you go hungry and then he fed you
the מן. Man. So again,
somehow the withholding of it is עונה, onah, so the same way
the withholding of sex is עונה, onah, but therefore the giving of
it, that word also means the obligation to give it. So it's
the same three but reversing which word it's learned out from. But
now we're going to get to more substantively different approaches. Top of
מ"ח. Mem chet. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
omer, שארה כסותה. She'erah kesutah.
So now he's going to read these as pairs. שאר כסות, She'er
kesut, which means לפום שארה תן כסותה, Le-fum she'erah ten kesutah,
based on her flesh as it were, give her her clothes. Meaning
it's like an adjective, it's qualifying the nature of the obligation of
clothes. שלא יתן לא של ילדה לזקנה ולא של זקנה לילדה. Shelo
yiten lo shel yaldah le-zekenah ve-lo shel zekenah le-yaldah. Don't give a
young woman, or literally a child, the clothes for an older woman,
or an older woman the clothes for a young woman. So it
describes what type of clothing to provide, appropriate clothing. כסותה ועונתה, Kesutah
ve-onatah, and then the similar pair of כסות ksut and עונה. onah.
לפום עונתה תן כסותה, Le-fum onatah ten kesutah,
according to her the time period, give her clothes. שלא יתן חדשים
בימות החמה ולא שחקים בימות הגשמים. Shelo yiten chadashim bi-yemot ha-chamah ve-lo
shechakim bi-yemot ha-geshamim. Don't give new clothes in the summer, new clothes
are thicker apparently they haven't been worn thin, so therefore they'll make
her hot. Don't
buy winter clothes in the summer and not worn clothes, which means
thin clothes, summer clothes, in the winter. Okay, so according to him
the only biblical obligation is clothes, which is pretty shocking. So he
thinks that there's no biblical obligation to have sex or there's no
biblical obligation to provide מזונות? mezonot? So maybe not. I mean מזונות
mezonot we had before it sounded like it was rabbinic, but even
sex? So there are some ראשונים Rishonim that say that some of
the תנאים Tannaim that don't say that עונה onah is a biblical
obligation, it's not that they're saying that it's not a biblical obligation,
they're saying that it's not like external to the fundamental identity definition
of marriage. They say that they might even go even further and
say that central to the nature of marriage is a sexual relationship.
And therefore it's not like, oh we're married plus I gotta provide
food and we have to have sex. No, no, no, the whole
nature of the marriage is a sort of a contract and a
relationship that's about actually having sex. The relevance of this is again
the question about a husband, for example, that's not able to have
sex with his wife. Let's say either he refuses, but let's just
say due to a physical state he's not able, can the wife
sue for divorce? Is it seen as, how much is it seen
that it's not considered
to be,
you can't consider us to be married if we're not having sex?
Okay, and that becomes an interesting discussion in the ראשונים, Rishonim, right,
if it's just an external obligation that maybe he's it's not out
of his control as opposed to seeing it as something that's central
to the very nature and identity of the marriage. So that is
that discussion around this, although here that's not spelled out, all it
says is that it identifies all these things in the פסוקים pesukim
to be talking about clothing. What about חופה? chuppah? You said before
that that was דרבנן. derabbanan. That was the פשט pshat of the
ברייתא. braita. all it says is identifying all these things in the
פסוקים *Pesukim* to be talking about clothing. Wait, the חופה *Chuppah*! You
said before that that was Rabbinic, that was the פשט *Pshat* of
the ברייתא braita *Braita* before. Okay. תני רב יוסף *Tani Rav Yosef*.
It is funny, right, of all the things to start saying you
have to provide clothing. תני *Tani* but we're not done. So now
we have one that says all three. We have two versions of
all three. We have one version just of clothes. Now we're going
to have another version that it's all about sex. תני רב יוסף
*Tani Rav Yosef*: שארה זו קירוב בשר *She'erah zu kiruv basar*. שארה
*She'erah* means the closest of flesh. שלא ינהג בה מנהג פרסיים *Shelo
yinhag bah minhag Parsiyim*, should not do like the Persians do, שמשמשין
מיטותיהן בלבושיהן *she-meshameshin mitosayhen belivushayhen*, that they have sex with their clothes
on, you know, it's sort of like the so every culture has
this apparently believes that there's this other exotic culture that has sex
through the through the hole in the sheet, right, that's the myth
about Jews. So here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has this as the
belief about the Persians, that they're wearing their nightclothes and they're having
sex and not actually sleeping together naked. מסייע ליה לרב הונא *Mesayeye
lei l'Rav Huna*, this supports רב הונא *Rav Huna*, דאמר רב הונא
*de'amar Rav Huna*, האומר Ha'omer, אי אפשי אלא אני בבגדי והיא בבגדה
*ha-omer ee efshi ela ani bevigdi vehi bevigdah*, if a man says
I refuse to have sex with my wife unless we're both wearing
clothes, meaning like they're in pajamas, you know, but we're not we're
not naked together, יוציא ויתן כתובה Ketubah. *yotzi venotein ketubah*. He has
to divorce and give the כתובה Kesubah *ketubah*. It's not enough that
he has sex. It has to be a sex with קירוב בשר
*kiruv basar*, with the coming together of the flesh. It has to
be a sex that they're together naked. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes
that husband and wife are sleeping together naked, which is why the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has a question that when the in שבת *Shabbos*
that when the woman is a נידה *niddah*, maybe they don't need
separate beds. Maybe it's enough that they're just wearing pajamas, and that
might be enough of a we don't rule that way. In the
end the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* concludes they need separate beds. But the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* thinks that that might be enough of a היכר
*hekker* because it assumes that if they're having sex, they're sleep they're
they're sleeping together naked, not just sleep I mean, I don't mean
just having sex together naked, yes that, but also meaning they're together
naked in the bed. So therefore if they're wearing some type of
pajamas that would be enough might be enough of a היכר *hekker*
says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that she's a נידה *niddah*. In the
end it concludes they need separate beds. So according to this, שארה
*she'erah* means sex. What does the other words in the פסוקים *pesukim*
mean? So here it becomes an interesting point that although we quote,
everybody knows רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, שארה כסותה ועונתה *she'erah kesusah va'onah*, clothes,
sex and food etcetera, right? The actual הלכה halakha, *halacha* according to
most ראשונים *Rishonim* is that the only biblical obligation is sex. That
actually clothing and מזונות *mezonot* are rabbinic. And that was the simple
language of the ברייתא braita *Braita* earlier, at least by the מזונות
*mezonot*. That those are the rabbinic obligations. Biblically it's only sex. So
what do the three words mean if it's all about sex? So
the רמב"ן *Ramban* says על התורה *al ha-Torah* that there's three aspects
of the sexual relationship between husband and wife, okay, which is שארה
*she'erah* means that they're not just having sex, you know, as the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* describes, with קירוב בשר *kiruv basar*, it's a coming
together of the two bodies and that they're together naked and that
it's really of a sense of a union and not just of
the act of sex itself. That's שארה *she'erah*. כסותה *kesutah*, he says
and he also says specifically this is again in the context of
the of the first wife who he might treat like as a
lowly wife and not with the right status. So he might say
oh well my real wife, the one I married not as a
slave as a free woman, she's the one I give the right
respect. This first wife, you know, I just go to her for
sex. So therefore it says no no no. Even that has to
be done in the right even the sex has to be done
in the right way. It's all about context, not just the act.
So therefore number one is it's the שארה *she'erah*, it's about the,
you know, the bodies coming together and not just about the simple
act of intercourse. And then the כסותה *kesutah* is he said is
that's about like the the the bedroom,
meaning the it doesn't literally just mean clothes, it means like the
bedsheets and the, you know, and and the bed and the way
the whole sort of environment is set up. That it's not done
as an act of just like like he says sort of like
going to see a prostitute, you know, it's done in a romantic
and respectful, you know, and in a way that's done as shows
that you treat that the husband's treating her as a wife and
not just as a sex object. So basically he said it means
the sheets and the pillows and the whole thing. They're not even
having they have the accoutrements. They're not having sex on the floor
is what he says, you know, they're having it on the marital
bed, okay, is how what he says כסותה *kesutah* means. And עונתה
*onatah* means again at regular times and as a sense of an
ongoing sense of connection and responsibility. Okay. So the רמב"ן *Ramban* says
these are all dimensions of the sexual life and that fits he
says that to well it certainly it certainly reflects an attitude towards
marital sex, but he also says it to fit the הלכה *halacha*
because הלכה *halacha* is that שארה וכסות *she'er ve'ksut* is really rabbinic,
even though we all think what do you mean it's in the
תורה *Torah*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* said so, but it's not clear what
those words mean. Okay. All right, so those are the husbands we're
going to mention anyway all this, ואזון *v'eizon*
yeah so we got the sex which might be why the sex
is separate because maybe that's a you know, that's the only biblical
one. Maybe these are all rabbinic. No, the only part that maybe
דאורייתא *de-Oraisa* that we put in our כתובה ketubah *ketubah*, meaning that
we make a reference to, would be the דחזי ליכי מוהר בתולייכי
*de-chazi lichi moar betulayichi* where is it? Yeah this is the מוהר
*moar*, this is the כתובה ketubah, *ketubah*, this is the sex. And
if you think that שארה וכסות *she'er ve'ksut* are rabbinic, are דאורייתא
*de-or* I mean שארה *she'erah* and ואזון *v'eizon* is what do you
call it, is מזונות *mezonot*, and פרנס *parneis* is probably כסות *ksus*.
So that there was something about דאורייתא *de-oraysa* over there. Oh yeah
the word דאורייתא *de-oraysa* only refers to the is only said about
the
200 כתובה ketubah, *ketubah*. Yeah. So we didn't exactly פסקן *paskin* our
כתובה *ketubah* what we should do. Yeah. It's a funny wording, מעלתיכי
me'altaychi, כאורחא. מעלתיכי, yeah. Right, so in the context of what you
just said. In other words, there it sounds like just like the
most perfunctory... That's interesting. Yeah, I was wondering about that. First of
all, the wording is very, right, mundane. Very prosaic. But I do
wonder, כאורח כל ארעא, ke'orcha kol ar'ah, you know, because because here
you also have like כהלכות גוברין יהודאין, kehilchos guvrin yehuda'in, right? So
that might mean in the, but that might mean, but again this
might be a similar word like כהלכות גוברין יהודאין, kehilchos guvrin yehuda'in,
meaning I'm going to do it in the right way, in the
way that's, you know, the upstanding type of a way to do
it. I'm not going to try to cheat and do it like,
you know, cut corners. So כאורח כל ארעא ke'orcha kol ar'ah might
be similar. I mean you could read it, you know, not just
okay, באורחא be'orcha as opposed to שלא כארחא, shelo ke'orcha, but it
could also mean in the context of the Rambam, you know, in
the proper way, in the way that's normally done, you know, and
so I think that's what I think the sense of it is.
Yeah. It would be interesting, I don't know if there's like a
discussion of exactly that phrasing, but that's the way I understood it,
that it parallels like כהלכות גוברין יהודאין. kehilchos guvrin yehuda'in. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. All right. רבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, now we get back to the משנה. Mishnah.
That was the entire discussion, I mean the גמרא Gemara will come
up but it's so funny how perfunctorily we dealt with, you know,
the reciprocal obligations and which are biblical, which are rabbinic. Now we're
done with כתובה. Back to the משנה, Mishnah, which is how much
does he have to spend to bury her. And רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says no fewer than two like flutes and a wailer, so
מקוננת. mekonenes. So the גמרא Gemara says, רבי יהודה אומר אפילו עני
שבישראל, Rabbi Yehuda omer afilu ani she-be-Yisrael, no matter how poor he
is, that's what he have to spend.
So the
גמרא Gemara says מכלל דתנא קמא mikh'lal de-Tanna Kamma סבר הני לא,
savar hani lo, that even this he doesn't have to do. So
היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אי דאורחה, ei de'orchah, if
it's her way to get this. Now what do you mean her
way? You only die once. So it means that this is how
women in her family or people in her family normally have been
buried with this standard. So מאי טעמא דתנא קמא, mai ta'ama de-Tanna
Kamma, why would the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma say that he's entitled
to do less than what her family standard is?
דאמר לה, de-amar lah, that they wouldn't have to. ואי לאו דאורחה,
ve-ei lav de'orchah, and if it wouldn't be the standard of her
family, so מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה, mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehuda, why does
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say it's necessary? So the גמרא Gemara says
לא צריכא, lo tzerikha, no, fine. כגון דאורחה דידיה ולאו אורחה דידה.
kegon de'orcheh dideyh ve-lav orchah didah.
That's the minimum standard for his family, but not the minimum standard
for her family. Her family maybe even gets by with less. תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma סבר, savar,
so here's the question: according to whose standard does the husband have
to provide for the wife? What does it mean clothes, how expensive,
what types of clothes, what it means food, what type of food,
right? So whose standard is she provided for? So everybody agrees minimally
he has to provide for her to the standard to which she
is accustomed. Let's say, however, he comes from a wealthier or higher
class family, does he have to provide for her to the standard
to which he is accustomed? So that's the question of עולה עמו
ואינה יורדת עמו. olah immo ve-einah yoredes immo. She goes up with
him and is not pulled down after him. So she gets, you
know, so she's not only entitled to her standard, but if his
standard is a higher one she's entitled to his as well. That's
a question whether we say that, whether he has to provide for
her according to his standard. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אפילו למאן דאמר afilu le-man de-amar סבר כי אמרינן עולה עמו ואינה
יורדת עמו, savar ki amrinan olah immo ve-einah yoredes immo, it's a
question whether we say it in this case after death. כי אמרינן,
ki amrinan, when do we say as a general rule עולה עמו
ואינה יורדת עמו, olah immo ve-einah yoredes immo, she goes up with
him and not down with him, so he has to provide according
to the higher of the two standards, his and her, הני מילי
מחיים. hani mili mikhayim.
That's in terms of while they're both alive, in terms of the
food and the clothing etc. אבל אחר מיתה, aval achar misa, now
that she's dead, לא, lo, then they no longer have a shared
life together anymore, she's already dead. So now he can just give
her what her family standard is in terms of the funeral costs.
Okay, ורבי יהודה סבר אפילו אחר מיתה. ve-Rabbi Yehuda savar afilu achar
misa.
No, even after death he is still, you know, taking care of
her as his wife, and he has to give her the standard,
the higher standard of him and her. So if his standard is
higher, he has to provide for her. Now of course it's funny
because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda made it sound like it wouldn't be
according to the גמרא Gemara way the גמרא Gemara is saying it,
is both of them have a very low standard he wouldn't have
to provide this for her, right? Which does not sound like רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda sort of saying like everybody
is entitled to this minimum standard. I don't care what they do
in practice or whatever, this is a minimum standard that everyone's entitled
to. The גמרא Gemara doesn't read it that way and it's a
question about whether after death the husband has to provide according to
his standard, his family standard, if it's higher than hers, her family
standard. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב
חסדא אמר מר עוקבא, Amar Rav Chisda amar Mar Ukva, הלכה כרבי
יהודה, halakha ke-Rabbi Yehuda, we rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that
it has to be according to his, the higher standard, even after
death. ואמר רב חסדא אמר מר עוקבא, Ve-amar Rav Chisda amar Mar
Ukva, מי שנשתטה, mi she-nishtateh,
let's say she's, the husband is now, has become a שוטה,
shoteh, has is...
is demented, dealing with some type of a psychotic episode and therefore
he cannot actually write out the checks and provide for his wife.
Who is taking care of his wife when he's in this state?
So גמרא Gemara says, and yeah, maybe she doesn't have her own
bank account. So בית דין יורדין לנכסיו וזנין ומפרנסין את אשתו. Beis
Din yordin l'nechasav v'zanin u'mefarnesin es ishto. Notice there the word זנין
ומפרנסין, zanin u'mefarnesin, right? ואזון ואפרנס. V'ezon v'afarnes. Okay, so,
and רש"י Rashi says by זנין ומפרנסין, zanin u'mefarnesin, רש"י Rashi has
מפרנסין mefarnesin if you look at the רש"י Rashi about twenty lines
down, לבוש וכסות. levush u'ksus. So there you have that pair which
is the pair in the כתובה and there you have the food
and the clothes. Okay, so בית דין Beis Din goes ahead and
they sell off his property, you know, if they need to, to
raise the money to provide for her, ובניו ובנותיו, u'banav u'bnosav, not
only to provide for his wife, but ובניו ובנותיו u'banav u'bnosav to
provide for his
kids, ודבר אחר, v'davar acher,
and another thing what the other thing is we'll see in a
minute. So they take care of paying his bills. אמר ליה רבינא
לרב אשי, Amar lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi, so רבינא Ravina said to
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, so מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, מאי שנא מהא
דתניא, mai shna mei'ha d'tanya,
how is it different from that which we taught? מי שהלך למדינת
הים, Mi she'halach l'mdinas hayam, he's not dealing with a psychotic episode
or something. He's just not around. He's gone on a business trip.
ואשתו תובעת מזונות, V'ishto tova'as mezonos,
and the wife says, hey, I've got to buy food and he
hasn't left me any money. So בית דין יורדין לנכסיו, Beis Din
yordin l'nechasav, same הלכה, בית דין Beis Din goes down to his
property and זנין ומפרנסין את אשתו zanin u'mefarnesin es ishto
and sells it off to feed his wife, אבל לא בניו ובנותיו,
aval lo banav u'bnosav, they don't sell off his property to feed
his kids, ולא דבר אחר, v'lo davar acher, or not for other
matters. We'll see what the other matters are in a minute. So
what's the difference? So as Michael correctly reminded us, there's no legal
obligation to feed one's kids. There is a legal obligation for a
husband to feed his wife, although obviously as a standard practice he
would feed his kids. So that's going to be the basis of
the answer. Let's take a look. אמר ליה, Amar lei, ולא שני
לך בין יוצא לדעת ליוצא שלא לדעת? v'lo shani lach bein yotzei
l'da'as l'yotzei shelo l'da'as?
Doesn't it make a difference to you whether a person is leaving
consciously and willingly or not consciously? If a guy goes and leaves
on a trip, he knows he has obligations to his wife and
his kids and he is disregarding them. To heck with them, he's
not providing, he's gone on his trip. So basically we can't force
him to pay for things he's not legally obligated. By willingly leaving
on his trip and not providing for his kids, he's basically saying
I'm not intending to feed my kids. Well, he's entitled to not
feed his kids, I mean he's not legally bound. Okay, and the
only thing we can act on are the things that he has
a legal obligation towards, which are feeding his wife. So that we
could sell off his property. That's when he leaves in right mind,
consciously, and he's just leaving a trip and not providing. If he
actually has gone crazy or, you know, cannot provide, you know, is
not in his right state of mind, so then we're going to
act based on what we can assume he would have done had
he been well. So that's an interesting question. Right, presumably, if before
this happened he was not providing for his kids, presumably we wouldn't
be entitled. That's a good point. Okay, but here we are sort
of acting on his behalf. We're not just exacting his legal obligations,
right? In the case where he just abandons his wife and family,
we can only act legally in terms of what he's entitled. Here,
where he's gone crazy, we're acting based on what we assume he
would have wanted and therefore we're continuing to provide for his kids.
Did you have a question? Doesn't analogy would also say that if
he left for a trip and failed to provide for his wife
as well, then in the case that he forgot or was negligent?
Yeah,
but he's not entitled to not provide for his wife. She has
a legal right and she can sue in court. That's what I'm
saying regarding the kids, so one wants to say they should get
the same treatment. You mean like maybe he forgot? Maybe he would
have wanted to but forgot? If he was accustomed to support his
children and then left without,
unless he's planning on not coming back. Right, yeah, I understand. But
I mean we're going to read this as a shirking of responsibilities,
not as an oversight. Right, why don't we read it as an
oversight? But maybe we're not entitled to, you know? Why are we
entitled to take money away from him? We should read it as
he's communicating that he's not attending to those responsibilities. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, מאי דבר אחר? mai davar acher? What's this other thing that
in the case of when he, you know, when he's not of
right mind, we actually assume he would, it's not a legal responsibility
but we assume like the kids, but we assume that he would
want to have paid for it? What is this other thing? מאי
דבר אחר? mai davar acher? רב חסדא אמר זה תכשיט. Rav Chisda
amar ze tachshit. So it's other obligations for his wife which are
not necessarily the strict legal obligation. It's not clothes, but it's more
like jewelry, or interestingly רש"י says jewelry is
actually רש"י says it means perfume. I don't know why he says
it means perfume rather than jewelry, but okay, maybe because perfume is
like an ongoing cost, whereas jewelry like since when do you buy
new jewelry on a regular basis? Anyway, but it's some type of
a thing for the wife that he would normally do but is
not his legal obligation. And again, that we'll do in a case
where he is when he... When he when he when he's when
he did not consciously abandon his family. Okay, I don't know. So
רב יוסף אמר צדקה. Rav Yosef amar tzedaka. How about giving how
about giving a certain amount to charity? Okay, maybe if he regularly
and again, the question is like you know what does he regularly
do? But let's say based on what he regularly do, he's you
know if he regularly gives $1,000 a year to charity and he's
now in
this you know and he has not been in his right mind,
do we continue to make that donation on his behalf? Okay, so
מאן דאמר תכשיט, man damar tachshit, if you say תכשיט, tachshit, כל
שכן צדקה kol sheken tzedaka that you would certainly therefore say צדקה.
tzedaka. Why? I'm sorry,
yeah,
מאי דאורחיה, mai d'oraishi, oh, so רש״י Rashi says it's going on
the opinion that you don't provide the דבר אחר davar acher when
he abandons his family. Okay, as opposed to the case where you
do, right? There's one ברייתא where you do, one ברייתא where you
don't. So he abandoned his family, you don't provide. If you don't
provide תכשיט, tachshit, you certainly don't provide צדקה. tzedaka. If you're not
going to do stuff for his own family, you're certainly not going
to do stuff for other people. מאן דאמר צדקה, man damar tzedaka,
but the one that says that you don't you know provide for
צדקה, tzedaka, אבל תכשיט יהבינן לה, aval tachshit yavinhu lah, we could
say that even if he's abandoned the family and he and you're
not going to feed the kids, you'll still provide the תכשיט tachshit
for the wife. Why? דלא ניחא ליה דתתנבל, delo nichla d'tinval, he
doesn't want his wife to be you know degraded. So it's interesting:
his kids, we'll assume he wants to abandon them and he consciously
left and therefore we're not going to provide for. But his wife,
and he also consciously left his wife, but in addition to taking
out the money for her clothes, we'll also take out the money
for her תכשיט. tachshit. Okay. אמר רבי חייא בר אבין אמר רב
הונא: Amar Rabi Chiya bar Avin amar Rav Huna: המשתלח למדינת הים
ומתה אשתו, Mishtalach limdinat hayam umeta ishto, he went to overseas and
his wife died. And now remember, he has a responsibility to bury
his wife, okay, that's the כתובה responsibility. בית דין יורדין לנכסיו וקוברין
אותה, Beis Din yordin linchasav vekovrin osah, so בית דין Beis Din
has to go ahead and pay for the you know cost, so
they sell off his property and they bury her לפי כבודו lefi
kvodo according to his status. גמרא says לפי כבודו ולא לפי כבודה?
lefi kvodo velo lefi kvodah? His status and not hers? But let's
say his status is lower than hers? And as we said before,
everybody agrees minimally it has to be based on the status that
she's entitled to. So גמרא says אימא אף לפי כבודה, eima af
lefi kvodah, even according to his status, meaning so you'll be the
higher of their two statuses. Of course it's always minimally according to
the status that she's in and her family, but if he's of
a higher status then it would be according to that level.
הא קמשמע לן עולה עמו ואינה יורדת עמו Hakmashmalan oleh imah ve'einah
yoredet imah like we said before, since רבי יהודה, Rabi Yehuda, that
it will go that he will be providing even for his status
at a higher
level that even after death he has to provide for her at
the higher of his and her statuses. Again, it's the תנא קמא.
tanna kamma. אמר רב מתנא: Amar Rav Matna: האומר, now רב מתנא
Rav Matna says last case within this: a guy's on his deathbed
and he says אם מתה לא תקברוה מנכסיי im meta lo tikberuha
minichasai that if my wife, if if when my wife dies, okay,
don't bury her from my property because notice if he's predeceasing her,
then he has no obligation to bury her. If he dies, she
collects her כתובה, she's out of there, right? The obligation to bury
was when she died before him. So here he is on the
deathbed and says after I die when she dies don't use my
money to bury her. Okay, he really doesn't even have to say
that, he didn't have an obligation at all. So גמרא says שומעין
לו. shomin lo. So
גמרא says מאי שנא כי אמר דנפלי נכסי קמי יתמי? mai shna
ki amar de'nafli nichsei kmai yasmi? So that's גמרא says מאי שנא
כי אמר, mai shna ki amar, what difference does it make when
if he says it דנפלי נכסי קמי יתמי? de'nafli nichsei kmai yasmi?
So because the property goes to the heirs and not to her
and the heirs don't have that obligation. So כי לא אמר נמי
נכסי קמי יתמי רמי, ki lo amar nami nichsei kmai yasmi rami,
even if he doesn't say anything, the heirs inherit, she gets her
כתובה, there's no obligation to bury her. Why does he have to
make any deathbed request? So גמרא says אלא סיפא ela safa and
change it, that's not what happened. האומר אם מת הוא לא תקברוהו
מנכסיו, Ha'omer im meis hu lo tikberuhu minichasav, here's a guy on
his deathbed and he's saying I'm about to die, don't use any
of the estate's funds to bury me.
Okay, because then it's the heirs' obligation to bury, but he's basically
telling his heirs I don't want you to spend any of your
money, any of the estate's money to bury me. So whose money
is it going to have to be spent? The
community's. So גמרא says אין שומעין לו, ein shomin lo, you don't
listen to him. You can actually take the cost of the funeral
out of the estate even if the man said he did not
want any money spent on it. לאו כל הימנו שיעשיר את בניו
ויפיל עצמו על הציבור. lav kol heimenu sheya'ashir et banav veyapil atzmo
al hatzibur. He has no right to make his sons richer by
and passing on the responsibility to the community in order to bury
him. All right, we will end here for today. So in a
case that the mother dies... Yeah... don't have to bury her? I
mean like that's what it sounded like.